BEN JARMAN

https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3527-5437

Capable researcher, with a recently completed doctorate on life imprisonment and varied research and practitioner experience in criminal justice. Brings first-class research training, as well as subject and project management expertise and strong people skills, to any role.

Qualifications

2024 PhD in Criminology | University of Cambridge

Passed with no corrections. Based on primary qualitative interviews and documentary research with 48 men serving life sentences in two English prisons, involving complex and sensitive issues relating to research ethics and requiring successful applications to HMPPS research

gatekeeping process

2017 MPhil in Criminological Research | University of Cambridge

Distinction. Trained to Masters standard in qualitative and quantitative research methods and criminological theory. Carried out original research based on ethnographic interviews with 18 men serving life

sentences at HMP Gartree.

2007 PGCE (Secondary History) | UCL Institute of Education

2003 BA(Hons), History & Religious Studies | University of Cambridge

Employment history

2022– Birkbeck, University of London | Senior Research Associate

Overall responsibility for research on the 'Unlocking potential' project, on law, policy, and practice relating to prison work and prison labour in the UK, the USA and Brazil. Designed study, carried out remote

interviews, secured ethics clearance and access to prisons in two

countries for ongoing fieldwork.

2021–2022 Prison Reform Trust, London | Knowledge Exchange Fellow

Collaboration: research and write-up of a prisoner policy consultation;

roundtable events with senior practitioners and stakeholders;

contributions to independent commission report on sentencing policy

(see Selected Publications below)

2017–2018 Institute of Criminology, Cambridge | Research Assistant

Research assistance on two projects: archival research commissioned by HMPPS to inform its responses to a judicial inquiry (see 'Publications' below); and analysis of qualitative interviews with senior prison leaders

2015–2016 Clinks, London | Valuing Volunteering Project Manager

Project manager for 'Valuing Volunteering in Prison' (see Selected Publications). Conducted practitioner and prisoner interviews, analysis, write-up, commissioned and project—managed contributions from 14 partner organisations, on a very tight timescale amid evolving funder

demands

2012-2015 Fine Cell Work, London | Volunteers & Programmes Manager Programme manager. Led support, recruitment, training, and management of volunteers working in 25 prisons nationally. Projectmanaged rollout of new accredited qualifications built around the programme 2011-2012 Clinks, London | Volunteering Development Officer Liaison with member organisations, research and write-up of case studies, good practice guidance and policy briefings 2010-2011 Quaker Council for European Affairs, Brussels | Programme Assistant International comparative research on prisoner social reintegration policies in Council of Europe member states 2007-2010 Immanuel College, Hertfordshire | Teacher of History & Politics Classroom teacher of pupils aged 11–18, professional mentor of trainee teachers, curriculum development specialist 2005-2006 St Francis Xavier College, London | Teacher of Student Support Classroom teacher and teaching assistant working with children with specific learning difficulties in a 16–19 FE college 2003-2004 Advertising Standards Authority, London | Investigations Executive Investigations into complaints from public and businesses about advertisements Other Volunteer posts as trustee/treasurer of two charities: a grant-giving trust; and the community chaplaincy at HMP Wandsworth. Grants, awards and professional memberships ESRC Studentship (co-funded by ESRC and Quakers in Britain) 2018-2022 2021 ESRC Knowledge Exchange fellowship (separate application to support my work with Prison Reform Trust) 2017 Proxime accessit, Manuel Lopez-Rey Graduate Prize (for overall performance in MPhil cohort) 2017-British Society of Criminology; European Society of Criminology 2014 Wrote successful bid for £150k to the Tudor Trust to set up a new mentoring service working through the HMP Wandsworth chaplaincy 2008 General Teaching Council for England: Qualified Teacher Status (Secondary History) 2003 Lightfoot Prize (for best performance in undergraduate dissertation)

Updated: November 2024

Selected publications

PhD thesis Jarman, B. .2024. 'Moral messages, ethical responses: Punishment and

self-governance among men serving life sentences for murder'.

Journal articles Jarman, B., & Heard, C. 2024. 'Prison work in law and reality:

comparative perspectives from Brazil, the UK, and the US'. European

Labour Law Journal.

Jarman, B. 2022. <u>'Life Imprisonment in Mature Adulthood: Adaptation, Risk, and Reform Later in the Life Course</u>'. *Prison Service Journal*.

levins, Alice, Ben Jarman, and Thea Thomasin Reimer. 2021. <u>'False Accounting: Why We Shouldn't Ask People Who Commit Crimes to Pay Their Debts to Society'</u>. *Working Notes*.

Jarman, Ben. 2020. 'Only One Way to Swim? The Offence and the Life Course in Accounts of Adaptation to Life Imprisonment'. The British Journal of Criminology.

Ben Jarman, and Caroline Lanskey. 2019. <u>"A Poor Prospect Indeed":</u> The State's Disavowal of Child Abuse Victims in Youth Custody, 1960–1990'. Societies.

Reports/briefings

Jarman, Ben, and Helen Fair. 2024a. 'Working Prisoners in the UK: Laws, Policies, and Practical Realities'. Institute for Crime & Justice Policy Research.

Jarman, Ben, and Helen Fair. 2024b. 'Working Prisoners in the USA: Laws, Policies, and Practical Realities'. Institute for Crime & Justice Policy Research.

Westbury, Margaret, Mathieu Candea, Jennifer Gabrys, Sara Hennessy, Ben Jarman, Kiera McNeice, and Curtis Sharma. 2022. <u>'Voice, Representation, Relationships: Report of the Open Qualitative Research Working Group</u>'.

Jarman, Ben, and Claudia Vince. 2022. <u>'Making Progress? What Progression Means for People Serving the Longest Sentences'</u>. Prison Reform Trust.

Independent Commission into the Experience of Victims and Long-Term Prisoners. 2022. <u>'Making Sense of Sentencing: Doing Justice to Both Victim and Prisoner'</u>. Drafted 2 chapters and edited report; credited as adviser.

Clinks. 2016. 'Valuing Volunteers in Prison: a review of volunteer involvement in prisons'. Led project and wrote report.

Casey, Joe, and Ben Jarman. 2011. '<u>The social reintegration of exprisoners in Council of Europe member states'</u>. Quaker Council for European Affairs.

Keynotes

Jarman, Ben. 2024. 'Getting What We Deserve? Imprisonment and the Challenge of Doing Justice (the 2024 Swarthmore Lecture)'.

Woodbrooke Quaker Learning and Research.

In preparation Dagan, N., & Jarman, B. Under review. 'Not *only* a murderer: Israeli

lifers' resistance to censure in the parole process', submitted to Law &

Social Inquiry, May 2024.

Selected knowledge exchange activities

2022 Planned and held two roundtable events to be held in March 2022,

bringing together senior policymakers and practitioners level to discuss the findings of PRT consultation on progression and parole for long-term prisoners in England & Wales (see 'Employment' above)

2021 Adviser to the Independent Commission on the Experiences of Victims

and Long–Term Prisoners, attending meetings, writing briefings, and drafting report chapters (see 'Employment' and 'Selected Publications'

above

2019 Led workshop on desistance and long–term prisoners for staff and

volunteers working with the Community Chaplaincy Association

Safeguarding Children in the Secure Estate 1960–2016 – training day at Newbold Revel (Prison Service College) for practitioners and policymakers, based on findings of the Safeguarding in the Secure

Estate project (see 'Employment' above)

Key research skills

Qualitative Research methods training: *Qualitative Research in Practice*.

Experienced in sensitive research topics; semi–structured interviews; focus groups; qualitative analysis with NVivo/Atlas.ti; historical/archival research; team research; research data management; Al transcription

Quantitative Research methods training: *Introducing Quantitative Analysis* and *Factor*

Analysis. Trained in use of SPSS and SurveyMonkey.

Publishing Self-taught user of document publication systems (WordPress,

Markdown, Typora, VSCode, Pandoc, Quarto); self-taught user of software packages and platforms relating to Open Access publishing and version control systems (PubPub, Symplectic Elements, Git); has published on the ethics of open research and data publication in

qualitative research featuring confidential and sensitive data

Prison–specific Negotiating access and recruiting participants in challenging

environments; working with prison staff; building rapport; conducting

research ethically in complex circumstances

Additional relevant skills and qualifications

Administration Excellent administrative skills; budgeting and financial management in

small charities; highly organised

IT Skilled user of commercial office packages (MS Office incl. Word, Excel,

PowerPoint etc., Sharepoint, Dropbox, Google Drive), and free and open–source alternatives for self-hosted servers (Linux, Docker,

LibreOffice, Nextcloud)

Fundraising Wrote successful bid for Wandsworth Community Chaplaincy Trust (see

above); contributed sections to successful Lottery bid at Fine Cell Work

Languages English (native speaker); French (intermediate spoken)

Referees

On request